<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!--

    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Compatibility goals in the Apache Harmony Classlib</title>
        <author email="dev@harmony.apache.org">Harmony Documentation Team</author>
    </properties>

    <body>

        <section name="Compatibility goals in the Apache Harmony Class Library">
            <p>
                <big>
                    <em>
                        The following guidelines are currently PROPOSED and being discussed on the
                        development mailing list <code>dev@harmony.apache.org</code>.  Please
                        direct comments and questions there.
                    </em>
                </big>
            </p>
            <p>
                The Harmony project class library (&quot;<b>classlib</b>&quot;) effort is committed
                to producing a set of class library code that not only Java compliant but is also
                compatible with existing Java implementations.
                This page describes the class library code guidelines for ensuring that compatibility.
            </p>

            <subsection name="The &quot;Reference Implementation&quot;">
                <a name="referenceImpl"/>
                <p>
                    The Harmony project
                    '<a href="http://harmony.apache.org/subcomponents/classlibrary">classlib</a>'
                    effort is producing a set of class library code that is compatible with
                    <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/docs/api/index.html">
                        the Java SE 5.0 API
                        specification
                    </a>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    At times (discussed below) it is necessary to augment the specification based on the
                    behavior of the reference implementation (RI) of the Java SE 5.0 specification.  In
                    such cases we use <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.5.0/download.jsp">
                        the latest
                        official release of the Java SE 5.0 RI
                    </a>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    We are aware that there are other compliant implementations of Java 5.0 available
                    but there is only one reference implementation of the Java specification.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="General Compatibility Guidelines">
                <p>
                    The following general guidelines apply when developing class library code for Apache
                    Harmony:
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <b>Comply with the Java Specification</b>
                            <p>
                                In the first instance we follow the description of each part of the class
                                library given in the <a href="#referenceImpl">Java specification</a>.  To
                                the large part, this adequately describes the behavior of the class library
                                implementation including methods, exceptions, and serialization.  However,
                                where the specification is silent on a particular issue facing the implementor,
                                or the described behavior is clearly illogical, then we follow the behavior
                                of the reference implementation.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <b>Follow the Reference Implementation</b>
                            <p>
                                The Reference Implementation (RI) is used to resolve issues that are not
                                adequately addressed in the specification.  In such cases we use the RI as a
                                guide to the compliant and expected behavior; however, developers <em>must</em>
                                ensure that the behaviour of the RI is determined soley through exercising the
                                public Java APIs -- specifically we avoid any notion of reverse engineering or
                                exposition of the RI's implementation by exercising non-API types and methods.
                            </p>
                            <p>
                                There are a few occasions where both the specification is quiet on a given
                                issue, and the RI exhibits behaviour that we would consider illogical.  In such
                                cases we discuss the issue on
                                <a href="../../mailing.html">
                                    the Harmony developers'
                                    mailing list
                                </a>, and code the class libraries to do what the development community
                                conclude is &quot;the logical thing&quot;.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <b>Do &quot;the Logical Thing&quot;</b>
                            <p>
                                The final decision about how a piece of code should behave, on those rare occasions
                                where the specification and RI do not provide a satisfactory answer, is reached
                                by concensus on the Harmony developers' mailing list.  Each issue is debated based
                                on it's individual circumstances, but the developers are aware that breaking popular
                                applications is invariably not &quot;the logical thing&quot; to do.
                                <p>
                                </p>
                                Once a decision has been made it is documented in the code comments and an issue
                                raised in <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HARMONY">
                                    the Harmony JIRA issue
                                    tracking system
                                </a> to record the conclusion.  It should be noted that very few issues
                                need to be resolved this way.
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Exception-throwing compatibility">
                <p>
                    There are a number of methods in the Java specification that describe the conditions under
                    which exceptions are thrown.  However, in most cases the specification does not describe all possible
                    exceptions that may be thrown, the order of exception throwing (i.e. where there are multiple
                    conditions that would result in an exception), and so on.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The Harmony class libary code aims to be fully compatible with the Reference Implementation (RI)
                    of the Java Specification by matching the exception characteristics of each method.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Harmony
                    <b>classlib</b> developers write test cases that deliberately cause exceptions to be thrown
                    so that we can match exception behaviour like-for-like.  Harmony class library code throws exceptions
                    of the same runtime class (or a subtype of that runtime class) as the RI, other than
                    in cases where the RI throws non-public types whereupon Harmony will throw an exception with the same public supertype.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Generally, we could refer to the following steps.
                    <ul>
                        <li>
                            <b>If RI is compliant with the Java Specification</b>
                            <p>
                                We shall follow RI's behavior, that is, throws exactly the same exception or a subclass of the exception.
                                <ul>
                                    <li>
                                        But there are some cases that RI throws an implementation specific exception,
                                        which is not in the Java Specification, we shall throw an equivalent Harmony specific exception,
                                        or its superclass in the Java Specification.
                                        <p>
                                            <i>
                                                e.g., If RI throws sun.io.MalformedInputException,
                                                we could throw org.apache.harmony.io.MalformedInputException or java.io.CharConversionException.
                                            </i>
                                        </p>
                                    </li>
                                </ul>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                        <li>
                            <b>If RI is not compliant with the Java Specification</b>
                            <p>
                                <ul>
                                    <li>
                                        If the Java Specification describes the exceptional situation explicitly,
                                        and RI throws different kind of exception or even does not throw any exception,
                                        we shall discuss them case by case in harmony-dev mailing list.
                                        <ul>
                                            <li>If we decide to follow RI, we will raise an "Non-bug differences from Spec" JIRA.</li>
                                            <li>If we decide to follow the Java Specification, we will raise an "Non-bug differences from RI" JIRA.</li>
                                        </ul>
                                    </li>
                                    <li>
                                        If the Java Specification does NOT describe the exceptional situation explicitly,
                                        and RI's behavior is either hard to reproduce or illogical, we shall discuss them case by case.
                                        And we may decide to:
                                        <ul>
                                            <li>Follow RI</li>
                                            <li>Follow the Java Specification</li>
                                            <li>Implement the functions in our own way</li>
                                        </ul>
                                    </li>
                                </ul>
                            </p>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="Serialization compatibility">
                <p>
                    The Harmony class library code aims to be serialization compatible with the reference
                    implementation (RI).
                </p>
                <p>
                    The Java Specification describes the serialized form of many Java types.  Where given, <b>classlib</b> will follow
                    the specified serialized form.  When the serialized form is <u>not</u> given we will ensure that the
                    serialization data is compatible with the RI by ensuring that objects serialized from the RI
                    can be read by Harmony's <b>classlib</b> code, and vice versa.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Serialization tests are part
                    of our regular test suite and typically rely on having the persistent form of serialized objects
                    written from the RI stored alongside our test suite code.
                </p>
                <p>
                    To indicate that we are serialization-compatible we define an explicit Stream Unique Identifier
                    (SUID) in each of the Harmony <b>classlib</b> serializable types that is equal to the SUID of
                    the corresponding type in the RI.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Where the RI produces a serialized form that cannot be replicated by Harmony (e.g. the RI serialized
                    form includes types that are not part of the Java specification) then Harmony cannot be
                    serialization compatible with the RI, and will both make a prominent note of such in the relevant
                    type's JavaDoc comment, and raise a JIRA issue that describes the incompatibility.
                </p>
            </subsection>

        </section>
    </body>
</document>
