<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

    <properties>
        <title>Apache Harmony Contribution Policy</title>
        <author email="dev@harmony.apache.org">Harmony Documentation Team</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Apache Harmony Contribution Policy">
            <p>
                Due to the oversight which we wish to provide for the Harmony community, the following
                process is used for committers, contributors and their contributions.
            </p>
            <p>
                In summary :
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    We are working to ensure that we have broad participation from the community,
                    at all experience levels and interests, but at the same time we are working to
                    minimize any risks to the ASF, the project and our community due to
                    inappropriate contributions of the intellectual property of others.
                </li>
                <li>
                    We adhere to the standard Apache process and contribution agreements, and
                    enhance them to gather information about contributor's previous experience with
                    similar technology. This information is used to ensure that the work
                    contributed to the project does not infringe the intellectual or other
                    property rights of others.
                </li>
                <li>
                    We have compartmentalized our repository and use fine-grained access control
                    to ensure broad participation while still ensuring that inappropriate or
                    questionable contributions do no occur.
                </li>
                <li>
                    We require every contributor to fill out an
                    <a href="auth_cont_quest.html">Authorized Contributor Questionnaire</a>,
                    which is used to help limit the risks to our source base from inappropriate
                    contributions.
                </li>
            </ul>
            <subsection name="Division of Repository">
                <p>
                    We have divided <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/svn.html">
                    our Subversion(SVN) repository</a> into sections. There are two main sections, the "standard"
                    section, for which the standard Apache process applies (namely, the standard
                    <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/icla.txt">Apache ICLA</a>
                    is all that is required) and the "enhanced" section, which requires any
                    committer to also be an Authorized Contributor. Project code is in the
                    "enhanced" section, and website, documentation and other miscellany is in
                    the "standard" section. For the purposes of illustration:
                </p>
<pre>
enhanced
    /admin
    /classlib
        /branches
        /tags
        /trunk
           /modules
              /applet
              /awt
              /beans
              /...
    /drlvm
       /trunk
           /build
           /src
           /vm
    /jchevm
    /tools
    /...

standard/
    /sandbox
    /site
    /tools
    /...
</pre>
                <p>
                    and we limit access within the enhanced part of the SVN by fine-grained
                    access control lists using information provided by Authorized Contributors,
                    as defined below.
                </p>
                <p>
                    We will be as liberal as possible - if your status as an Authorized Contributor
                    doesn't prevent it, access should be granted to any part of the SVN repository.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Strict Limits on Committer Contribution">
                <p>
                    Committers can only commit contributions to the repositories
                    that they personally created <i>specifically for contribution to Apache Harmony.</i>
                    This is the standard stream of fresh original work, small enhancements
                    and patches that are the normal flow of project life.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The purpose of
                    this rule is to explicitly prohibit re-purposed "bulk" code
                    that the contributor believes is their original work from being
                    added to the codebase without explicit oversight and acceptance.
                    We can still accept contributions like that, but will track them explicitly
                    as Bulk Contributions.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Policy for Committers">
                <p>
                    Each committer is required to complete a standard
                    <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/">Apache Individual Contributor License Agreement</a>.
                    This document asserts that the contributor is licensing their
                    material to the ASF under the Apache license and is their original work (there's some other details).
                    This document is maintained and managed by the Secretary of the Apache Software Foundation.
               </p>
                <p>
                    In order for a committer to become an Authorized Contributor to Harmony, each committer
                    is also required to complete the
                    <a href="auth_cont_quest.html">Authorized Contributor Questionnaire</a> and submit it to
                    <a href="mailing.html">the Harmony PMC</a>.
                </p>
                <p>
                    We encourage every committer, if appropriate, to have their employer execute a
                    <a href="http://www.apache.org/licenses/">Apache Corporate Contributor License Agreement</a>.
                    Note that this is recommended, but not required.
                </p>
            </subsection>
            <subsection name="Policy for Bulk Contributions">
                <p>
                    Any software or other contribution that was not created explicitly for
                    Apache Harmony <i>in</i> the Apache Harmony project is considered to
                    be a 'Bulk Contribution'. This status is independent of the purpose
                    or author of said contribution. For example:
                </p>

                <ul>
                    <li> Personal utilities that a committer always uses on projects</li>
                    <li> Code from other open source projects that have a compatible license</li>
                    <li> Code from proprietary projects for which the donor has clear title</li>
                </ul>
                <p>
                    Any Bulk Contribution  :
                </p>
                <ol>
                    <li>Will be donated via the project bug tracking system (JIRA) as a contribution under the Apache License</li>
                    <li>Will be accompanied by a Software Grant or CCLA which will be registered with the Apache Incubator</li>
                    <li>Will be registered in the Apache Harmony Bulk Contribution Repository
                        via a <a href="bulk_contribution_checklist.html">Bulk Contribution Checklist</a>
                    </li>
                    <li> Will be made by an Authorized Contributor to Harmony (defined above)</li>
                </ol>

                <p>
                    The Bulk Contribution Repository is a separate place in our administrative SVN in which each contribution
                    is committed, in it's entirety, before being combined with the project codebases. We do this to
                    ensure that we have a clear and unambiguous record of any repurposed software that was contributed or
                    brought into the project source tree. Along with the source or other contributed materials, the
                    contribution will also include a description of the software and the name of the Authorized Contributor
                    that made the donation.
                </p>
                <p>
                    We strongly urge any potential contributor to carefully examine their candidate for contribution
                    before offering to the project. To that end, we have started collecting information on tools and
                    other aids to help in this process, and it can be found <a href="code_scan_tools.html">here</a>.
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>


