<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Open Source Java SE</title>
    <author email="dev@harmony.apache.org">Harmony Documentation Team</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Welcome to Apache Harmony - Open Source Java SE">

      <p>
        <big>Welcome to Apache Harmony - Open Source Java SE.</big>
      </p>

      <p>
        Apache Harmony is
        the Java SE project of the
        <a href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation</a>.
        Please help us make this a world class, certified implementation of the
        Java Platform Standard Edition!
      </p>
      <p>
        The aim of the project is to produce a large and healthy community
        of those interested in runtime platforms tasked with creation of:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          A compatible, independent implementation of the Java SE 5
          JDK under the Apache License v2
        </li>
        <li>
          A community-developed modular runtime (VM and class library)
          architecture.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        We aim to support wide range of different platforms. The main criteria
        for whether a particular platform is supported or not is the involvement
        of people in running tests on regular basis, reporting build status, finding
        and fixing bugs for that platform, and so on. We have
        <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/harmony/Platforms_to_Run_Harmony_Development_Kit_on">
          a
          list of platforms
        </a> we are actively maintaining at the moment.
      </p>
      <p>
        Please see the following "Getting Started" guides:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="quickhelp_users.html">Getting Started for Harmony Users</a>: for those
          that wish to use <a href="download.cgi">pre-built snapshots</a> of Apache Harmony
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="quickhelp_contributors.html">Getting Started for Harmony Contributors</a>: for those
          that wish to checkout and build the source of Apache Harmony.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section name="Harmony News">
      <dl>
        
        <dt>5.0 M4 stable build has been released</dt>
        <dd>
          The Apache Harmony team are pleased to announce the immediate availability
          of Apache Harmony 5.0M4.  This is the latest stable build of the Harmony project
          with numerous enhancements including new JIT optimizations, functional
          and coverage enhancements throughout the class libraries, improved VM threading
          design, and support for full hardware addressability on 64 bit platforms.
          <p/>
          The build is available for
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi#M4-r603534">download</a>.
          Please send your feedback to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2007-12-19</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>We now accept bug reports on other languages.</dt>
        <dd>
          Users may now submit bug reports, improvement suggestions or patches on their native languages.
          We currently understand English, Chinese, and Russian. 
         (<i>2007-10-25</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>5.0 M3 stable build has been released</dt>
        <dd>
          The build is targeted primarily to improving overall stability and
          performance. This build contains the following enhancements:
          an innovative fast byte code verifier, lazy resolution in all JIT
          modes on IA32 platforms, support for Java6.0 classes in DRLVM.<p/>
          Other areas that were improved include:
          <ul>
            <li>
              Bytecode mapping in JIT - exception stack traces became more
              comprehensive
            </li>
            <li>
              Threading support was partially re-factored towards improvement
              of reliability and maintainability
            </li>
            <li>
              JIT-based JVMTI debug mode speed up by a factor of 3
            </li>
            <li>
              Stability of Swing and AWT code on Windows
            </li>
         </ul>
         The build is available for
         <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi#M3-r580985">download</a>.
         Please send your feedback to
         <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
         (<i>2007-10-09</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Harmony 5.0 M2 Available</dt>
        <dd>
          We are pleased to announce the second stable build "5.0 M2".
          In this build overall stability was improved, switch to GCv5 was made,
          a lot of JIT optimizations were implemented, memory consumption was
          significantly improved, API completeness came to 99.06% (without endorsed specs)
          and many bugs were fixed. Apache Harmony encourage users to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi#M2-r551077">download</a>
          and try the runtime or development kit, and report their experiences to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2007-06-30</i>)
        </dd>
      </dl>

      <p>
      <i>Archived articles are <a href="newshistory.html">here</a></i>.
      </p>
    </section>

    <section name="Project Status">
      <p>
        How are we doing? We're making steady progress:
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          JRE and HDK snapshots <a href="http://people.apache.org/builds/harmony/snapshots/">available</a>
        </li>
        <li>Up-to-date 
        <a href="http://people.apache.org/~varlax/harmony-integrity/">code integrity status</a>
        is tracked automatically on all supported platforms</li>
        <li>
          JRE can run popular programs like Apache Tomcat, Eclipse, Maven, Derby, Ant
        </li>
        <li>
          More than
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/subcomponents/classlibrary/status.html">99% of Java 5 API complete</a>.
          (not compatible, just completed)
        </li>
        <li>More than 1.25 Million Lines of Code</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
