<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Open Source Java SE</title>
    <author email="dev@harmony.apache.org">Harmony Documentation Team</author>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Welcome to Apache Harmony - Open Source Java SE">

      <p>
        <big>Welcome to Apache Harmony - Open Source Java SE.</big>
      </p>

      <p>
        Apache Harmony is
        the Java SE project of the
        <a href="http://www.apache.org/">Apache Software Foundation</a>.
        Please help us make this a world class, certified implementation of the
        Java Platform Standard Edition!
      </p>
      <p>
        The aim of the project is to produce a large and healthy community
        of those interested in runtime platforms tasked with creation of:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          A compatible, independent implementation of the Java SE 5
          JDK under the Apache License v2
        </li>
        <li>
          A community-developed modular runtime (VM and class library)
          architecture.
        </li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        We aim to support wide range of different platforms. The main criteria
        for whether a particular platform is supported or not is the involvement
        of people in running tests on regular basis, reporting build status, finding
        and fixing bugs for that platform, and so on. We have
        <a href="http://wiki.apache.org/harmony/Platforms_to_Run_Harmony_Development_Kit_on">
          a
          list of platforms
        </a> we are actively maintaining at the moment.
      </p>
      <p>
        Please see the following "Getting Started" guides:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>
          <a href="quickhelp_users.html">Getting Started for Harmony Users</a>: for those
          that wish to use <a href="downloads.html">pre-built snapshots</a> of Apache Harmony
        </li>
        <li>
          <a href="quickhelp_contributors.html">Getting Started for Harmony Contributors</a>: for those
          that wish to checkout and build the source of Apache Harmony.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </section>
    <section name="Harmony News">
      <dl>
        <dt>Windows x86-64 (64-bit) Snapshots Available</dt>
        <dd>
          We now are offering Harmony binaries for the x86-64 architecture under
          Windows. For more information, please
          see our <a href="downloads.html">downloads</a> page.
          (<i>2007-05-14</i>)
        </dd>
        <dt>First Milestone Available Now</dt>
        <dd>
          Apache Harmony are pleased to announce the the first stable build "5.0 M1".  The code,
          which was previously made available as "snapshot r533500", underwent additional testing
          after a period of stabalization in the ongoing development of a full release.  Apache Harmony
          5.0 M1 represents our best build so far, and we encourage users to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/downloads.html">download</a> and try the runtime
          or development kit, and report their experiences to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2007-04-30</i>)
        </dd>
        <dt>Harmony Classlib Enabled Version of JRockit VM Available for Project Use</dt>
        <dd>
          BEA announced the <a href="http://dev2dev.bea.com/jrockit/jrockitVM">availability</a> of
          an evaluation version of JRockit, their world-class JVM, that works
          with the Apache Harmony class library. Distibuted by BEA under a binary, evaluation-only
          license, this not only demonstrates the portablity of the
          <a href="subcomponents/classlibrary/index.html">Apache Harmony class library</a>,
          it also adds a valuable tool to help us as we continue building our independent implementation
          of Java SE.
          (<i>2007-01-30</i>)
        </dd>
        <dt>JDK Snapshot Available</dt>
        <dd>
          Apache Harmony now has a JDK snapshot available, that includes javac, keytool,
          and others. While not complete, it's our first step towards the standard
          JDK distribution format expected by developers. For more information, please
          see our <a href="downloads.html">downloads</a> page.
          (<i>2006-12-27</i>)
        </dd>
        <dt>Linux x86-64 (64-bit) Snapshots Available</dt>
        <dd>
          We now are including support for the x86-64 architecture under Linux.
          For more information, please
          see our <a href="downloads.html">downloads</a> page.
          (<i>2006-12-14</i>)
        </dd>
        <dt>Apache Harmony: Top-Level Project of the Apache Software Foundation</dt>
        <dd>
          Apache Harmony is now a top-level project of the Apache Software Foundation.
          On October 25th, the Board of Directors voted to make Apache Harmony a
          top-level project, and on October 29th the Apache Incubator PMC voted to
          graduate Harmony from the Apache Incubator, having satisfied the Incubator's
          requirements for community governance and IP oversight. We're in the process
          of transitioning our resources and infrastructure over, so please be patient
          while we do our move.
          (<i>2006-10-29</i>)
        </dd>
      </dl>
        <p>
            <i>
                Archived articles are <a href="newshistory.html">here</a></i>.
        </p>
    </section>
    <section name="Project Status">
      <p>
        How are we doing? We're making steady progress:
      </p>
      <ol>
        <li>
          JRE and HDK snapshots <a href="http://people.apache.org/builds/harmony/snapshots/">available</a>
        </li>
        <li>
          JRE can run popular programs like Apache Tomcat, Eclipse, Maven, Derby, Ant
        </li>
        <li>More than 95% of Java 5 API complete. (not compatible, just completed)</li>
        <li>More than 1.25 Million Lines of Code</li>
      </ol>
    </section>
  </body>
</document>
