<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->

<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Older Harmony News</title>
        <author email="dev@harmony.apache.org">Harmony Documentation Team</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Older Harmony News">
            <dl>
                <dt>New JRE and HDK Snapshots Posted</dt>
                <dd> Our <a href="downloads.html">latest snapshots</a> have
                        lots of new fixes and features. The VM has a new GC,
                        almost complete JVMTI, and now can co-exist with
                        <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/jdk/harmony">the IBM VME</a> in
                        the Harmony JRE structure. Our classlibrary continues to grow with new
                        classes, notably CORBA, thanks to <a href="http://incubator.apache.org/yoko">
                        Apache Yoko</a>.
                        Also, the classlibrary includes many new fixes and updates.
                        Choose the JRE to test your favorite applications, and
                        <a href="mailing.html">give us feedback</a> on how
                        we are doing, or use the HDK to enable faster development of the Harmony classlibrary.
                        (<i>2006-09-28</i>)
                 </dd>
                <dt>Can Apache Harmony Help Sun Open Java?</dt>
                <dd>We're happy to <a href="http://www.businessreviewonline.com/os/archives/2006/08/open_source_jav.html">help</a>
                        (<i>2006-08-16</i>)</dd>
                <dt>New Snapshot Posted</dt>
                <dd>Lots of fixes and additions in the latest snapshot. (<i>2006-08-16</i>)</dd>
                <dt>DRLVM Documentation Update</dt>
                <dd>Check our new documentation on <a href="subcomponents/drlvm/index.html">DRLVM</a>
                        including guides for building, using, debugging, GC architecture and execution manager
                        architecture. (<i>2006-08-05</i>)</dd>
                <dt>New HDK and JRE Snapshots Available</dt>
                <dd>New <a href="http://people.apache.org/builds/harmony/snapshots/">snapshots</a>
                        of the HDK and JRE are now available with lots of bugfixes. (<i>2006-08-04</i>)
                </dd>
                <dt>HDK and JRE Snapshots Available</dt>
                <dd>Harmony now <a href="http://people.apache.org/builds/harmony/snapshots/">offers a snapshot</a>
                        of it's JRE and HDK builds.
                        The JRE snapshot is our in-progress Java Runtime Environment,
                        including both the virtual machine and classlibrary. Note that
                        this isn't stable, complete or compatible software. However,
                        you can use this to run your favorite Java applications and
                        help the project find and fix bugs, and help direct our efforts
                        to complete the most popular parts of the classlibrary first. The HDK
                        snapshot is a developers build, complete with classlibrary jars and
                        native libraries, header files, and build scripts. (<i>2006-07-22</i>)
                    </dd>
                <dt>New class library snapshot build available</dt>
                <dd>A new stable snapshot of the class libraries code is available
                        for download from the <a href="downloads.html">Harmony downloads page</a>.
                        These are made available for people to evaluate and experiment
                        with the code. This snapshot contains the recently integrated
                        Swing, AWT, and Java2D code. As always, please report bugs
                        (and successes!) to the <a href="mailing.html">Harmony developers mailing list</a>.
                        (<i>2006-06-30</i>)
                  </dd>
                <dt>AWT, Java2D and Swing Code Contribution</dt>
                <dd>On May 30th, 2006 the Apache Harmony project received a
                        <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HARMONY-528">
                        substantial contribution</a> of class library code into the project.
                        The code for AWT, Java2D, and Swing implementation has been contributed by Alexey
                        Petrenko on behalf of Intel corp. The full announcement can be found
                        on the <a href="mailing.html">Harmony developers mailing list</a>. Thanks to
                        Alexey and his colleagues in the Intel Middleware Products Division!
                        (<i>2006-05-31</i>)
                </dd>
                <dt>New class library snapshot build available</dt>
                <dd> A new stable snapshot of the class libraries code is available
                        for download from the <a href="downloads.html">Harmony downloads page</a>.
                        There are source and binary downloads available for people to
                        evaluate and experiment with the code. As always, please report bugs
                        (and successes!) to the <a href="mailing.html">Harmony developers mailing list</a>.
                        (<i>2006-05-12</i>)
                   </dd>
                <dt>DRL Virtual Machine Contribution</dt>
                <dd>  On May 3rd, 2006 the Apache Harmony project received a
                        <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HARMONY-438">
                        substantial contribution </a> of virtual machine (VM) code into the project,
                        containing a JIT, core VM, GC, bytecode verifier, etc. This was contributed by
                        Andrey Chernyshev on behalf of Intel Corp. The full announcement can
                        be found on the <a href="mailing.html">Harmony developers mailing list</a>.
                        (<i>2006-05-03</i>)</dd>
                <dt>Java Security Code Contribution</dt>
                <dd>On December 30th, 2005 the Apache Harmony project accepted additional
                        class library code into the project. The code had been contributed by
                        Mikhail Loenko on behalf of Intel corp. The new class library code
                        includes security, cryptography, javax.net and unit tests. Thanks to
                        Mikhail and his collegues in the Intel Managed Runtime Division!
                        (<i>2006-01-16</i>)
                </dd>
                <dt>VM Interface and Core Classes Contribution</dt>
                <dd>IBM has offered the Apache Harmony project a set of core
                        Java classes and an implementation of a VM/class library
                        interface. Tim Ellison wrote:<br />
                        <i>
                            "I'm delighted to be able to make a code contribution to the
                            Harmony project on behalf of IBM. The code comprises a concrete implementation
                            of the interface between virtual machine and class library that we have
                            been discussing recently, together with a set of core Java classes."
                        </i><br />
                        This contribution is sufficient to run Ant and the Eclipse Java
                        compiler, to provide a basic self-hosting environment. IBM also
                        made a version of their J9 VM
                        <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/jdk/harmony">
                        available </a> for use by the project in evaluating this contribution.
                        Thanks Tim and IBM :) (<i>2005-11-08</i>)
                </dd>
                <dt>"Bootstrap JVM" Contributed to Apache Harmony</dt>
                <dd> Daniel Lydickto the Harmony project of a basic Java Virtual Machine entitled
                        the "Apache Harmony Bootstrap JVM." Dan offered the VM with the following goals in mind:
                        <ul>
                            <li>Basic platform for learning about VMs</li>
                            <li>Boostrap and runtime framework for our eventual 'production' VM</li>
                            <li>Help spur architectural discussion about core component designs</li>
                        </ul>
                        Thanks Dan! (<i>2005-09-30</i>)
                </dd>
                <dt>Source for JCVM Contributed to Apache Harmony</dt>
                <dd>Archie Cobbs has offered for contribution to the Apache Harmony project
                        a copy of the <a href="http://jcvm.sourceforge.net/">JCVM</a> codebase. Come and
                        help us build on this interesting VM. Thanks Archie! (<i>2005-09-25</i>)
                </dd>
                <dt>Project accepted by Apache Incubator</dt>
                <dd>The Apache Harmony project was accepted formally accepted for
                        inubation by the Apache Incubator PMC. (<i>2005-05-18</i>)
                </dd>
            </dl>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
