<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements. See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License. You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->

<document>
    <properties>
        <title>Older Harmony News</title>
        <author email="dev@harmony.apache.org">Harmony Documentation Team</author>
    </properties>
    <body>
        <section name="Older Harmony News">
        <!-- Please maintain reverse chronological order of new stories -->
        <p style="text-align: right"> <a href="newshistory.ru.html">RU </a>| EN</p>
        <dl>

        <dt>Apache Harmony 5.0 M11 now available</dt>
        <dd>
          The Apache Harmony development team are pleased to announce that
          Apache Harmony 5.0M11 is available for immediate download from
          the project website.
          <p/>

          Apache Harmony 5.0M11 is the latest stable build containing
          <a href="http://tinyurl.com/mb6yqp">over 60 bug fixes</a>
          and enhancements across a number of modules.
          <p/>

          As usual source code, binary builds and Debian packages are
          available from our
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi">download site</a>.
          Please send any feedback on these builds to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2009-09-01</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Apache Harmony 5.0 M10 declared!</dt>
        <dd>
          The Apache Harmony development team are pleased to announce that
          Apache Harmony 5.0M10 is available for immediate download from
          the project website.
          <p/>

          Apache Harmony 5.0M10 is the latest stable build containing
          <a href="http://tinyurl.com/mkq4bv">over 50 bug fixes</a>
          plus notable improvements to the JavaDoc comments in a number
          of modules.
          <p/>

          As usual, source code and binary builds and Debian packages are
          available from our
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi">download site</a>.
          Please send any feedback on these builds to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.
          (<i>2009-06-13</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Apache Harmony 5.0 M9 available for download!</dt>
        <dd>
          The Apache Harmony team are pleased to announce the immediate
          availability of Apache Harmony 5.0M9.
          <p/>

          Apache Harmony 5.0M9 is the latest stable build containing
          <a href="http://tinyurl.com/d6tu7w">numerous bug fixes</a>
          and enhancements including:
          <ul>
              <li>performance: across multiple areas, including class library improvements
                  and JIT compiler global propagation optimizations, integer MUL/DIV/REM
                  strength reduction, and so on.</li>
              <li>pack200: a new implementation of the JSR-200 compression technology
                  for Java bytecodes.</li>
              <li>porting work: in the class libraries for AIX and zOS operating systems.</li>
              <li>bug fixing: focus on our test case enhancements, and on passing the
                  Eclipse Test Suite.</li>
          </ul>
          <p/>

          Source code and binary builds are available from the project
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi">download site</a>.
          Please send feedback to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2009-04-15</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Apache Harmony 5.0 M8 now available</dt>
        <dd>
          The Apache Harmony team are pleased to announce the immediate
          availability of Apache Harmony 5.0M8.
          <p/>

          Apache Harmony 5.0M8 is the latest stable build containing numerous bug
          fixes, and enhancements to the policytool and pack200 support.
          <p/>

          Source code and binary builds are available from the project
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi">download site</a>.
          Please send feedback to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2008-11-20</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Apache Harmony 5.0 M7 is available!</dt>
        <dd>
          The Apache Harmony team are pleased to announce the immediate availability
          of Apache Harmony 5.0M7.  This is the latest stable build of the Harmony project
          with numerous enhancements and bug fixes including:
          <ul>
            <li>new performance improvements, especially in object serialization and unpack200 decoding</li>
            <li>a new 'javap' the class file disassembler tool, and alpha version of 'policytool' the security policy management tool</li>
            <li>bug fixes and functional enhancements throughout the class libraries, especially in the Swing widget toolkit</li>
            <li>...and many more</li>
          </ul>
          <p/>
          
          We would particularly like to thank our Google Summer of Code students
          András Belicza (policytool) and Tharindu Mathew (Swing enhancements),
          and welcome them to the project!
          <p/>
          
          The build has been replicated to the download sites, and we recommend that
          everyone update their current version to Apache Harmony 5.0M7.
          <p/>
          
          The build is available for
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi">download</a>.
          Please send your feedback to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2008-08-28</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Jikes RVM 3.0 + Apache Harmony!</dt>
        <dd>
          Ian Rogers recently announced exciting news of support for Harmony
          class libraries running on the Jikes RVM:<p/> 
          <i> 
            "We are pleased to announce the release of Jikes RVM 3.0, an
            open-source meta-circular JVM written in Java.  A new feature of
            the release is initial support for Apache Harmony's class library."
          </i><p/>
          See the full announcement and details of how to combine the two projects
          in <a href="http://markmail.org/message/5rehnbf2qj5xhiob">Ian's
          mailing list posting</a>.
          (<i>2008-08-27</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Microemulator code contribution</dt>
        <dd>
          Apache Harmony has broadened it's scope of code implementing the Java
          platform APIs with the acceptance of a substantial code contribution
          from the authors of Microemulator.
          <p/>
          Microemulator is a pure Java implementation of Java ME APIs in Java SE.  With
          the emulator code it becomes possible to run MIDlet (MIDP/CLDC) based
          applications as a standalone Java application or as web browser applet.
          <p/>
          Thanks to Bartek, Vlad, and Michael for this contribution to Apache Harmony!
          (<i>2008-06-09</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Apache Harmony 5.0 M6 is available!</dt>
        <dd>
          The Apache Harmony team are pleased to announce the immediate availability
          of Apache Harmony 5.0M6.  This is the latest stable build of the Harmony project
          with numerous enhancements and bug fixes including:
          <ul>
            <li>new JIT optimizations</li>
            <li>functional and coverage enhancements throughout the class libraries</li>
            <li>improved VM threading design</li>
            <li>support for full hardware addressability on 64 bit platforms</li>
            <li>new appletviewer and unpack200 tools</li>
            <li>...and many more</li>
          </ul>
          
          The build has been replicated to the download sites, and we recommend that
          everyone update their current version to Apache Harmony 5.0M6.
          <p/>
          The build is available for
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi#M6-r653525">download</a>.
          Please send your feedback to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2008-05-22</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>5.0 M5 now available</dt>
        <dd>
          The Apache Harmony team are pleased to announce the immediate availability
          of Apache Harmony 5.0M5.  This is the latest stable build of the Harmony project
          with numerous enhancements and bug fixes.  The build is being replicated to the
          download sites, and we recommend that everyone update their current version to
          Apache Harmony 5.0M5.
          <p/>
          The build is available for
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi#M5-r629320">download</a>.
          Please send your feedback to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2008-02-29</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>5.0 M4 stable build has been released</dt>
        <dd>
          The Apache Harmony team are pleased to announce the immediate availability
          of Apache Harmony 5.0M4.  This is the latest stable build of the Harmony project
          with numerous enhancements including new JIT optimizations, functional
          and coverage enhancements throughout the class libraries, improved VM threading
          design, and support for full hardware addressability on 64 bit platforms.
          <p/>
          The build is available for
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi#M4-r603534">download</a>.
          Please send your feedback to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2007-12-19</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>We now accept bug reports on other languages.</dt>
        <dd>
          Users may now submit bug reports, improvement suggestions or patches on their native languages.
          We currently understand English, Chinese, and Russian. 
         (<i>2007-10-25</i>)
        </dd>
        
        <dt>5.0 M3 stable build has been released</dt>
        <dd>
          The build is targeted primarily to improving overall stability and
          performance. This build contains the following enhancements:
          an innovative fast byte code verifier, lazy resolution in all JIT
          modes on IA32 platforms, support for Java6.0 classes in DRLVM.<p/>
          Other areas that were improved include:
          <ul>
            <li>
              Bytecode mapping in JIT - exception stack traces became more
              comprehensive
            </li>
            <li>
              Threading support was partially re-factored towards improvement
              of reliability and maintainability
            </li>
            <li>
              JIT-based JVMTI debug mode speed up by a factor of 3
            </li>
            <li>
              Stability of Swing and AWT code on Windows
            </li>
         </ul>
         The build is available for
         <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi#M3-r580985">download</a>.
         Please send your feedback to
         <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
         (<i>2007-10-09</i>)
        </dd>
        
        <dt>Harmony 5.0 M2 Available</dt>
        <dd>
          We are pleased to announce the second stable build "5.0 M2".
          In this build overall stability was improved, switch to GCv5 was made,
          a lot of JIT optimizations were implemented, memory consumption was
          significantly improved, API completeness came to 99.06% (without endorsed specs)
          and many bugs were fixed. Apache Harmony encourage users to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi#M2-r551077">download</a>
          and try the runtime or development kit, and report their experiences to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2007-06-30</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Windows x86-64 (64-bit) Snapshots Available</dt>
        <dd>
          We now are offering Harmony binaries for the x86-64 architecture under
          Windows. For more information, please
          see our <a href="download.cgi">downloads</a> page.
          (<i>2007-05-14</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>First Milestone Available Now</dt>
        <dd>
          Apache Harmony are pleased to announce the first stable build "5.0 M1".  The code,
          which was previously made available as "snapshot r533500", underwent additional testing
          after a period of stabilization in the ongoing development of a full release.  Apache Harmony
          5.0 M1 represents our best build so far, and we encourage users to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/download.cgi">download</a> and try the runtime
          or development kit, and report their experiences to
          <a href="http://harmony.apache.org/mailing.html">the Harmony mailing list</a>.  
          (<i>2007-04-30</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Harmony Classlib Enabled Version of JRockit VM Available for Project Use</dt>
        <dd>
          BEA announced the <a href="http://dev2dev.bea.com/jrockit/jrockitVM">availability</a> of
          an evaluation version of JRockit, their world-class JVM, that works
          with the Apache Harmony class library. Distibuted by BEA under a binary, evaluation-only
          license, this not only demonstrates the portability of the
          <a href="subcomponents/classlibrary/index.html">Apache Harmony class library</a>,
          it also adds a valuable tool to help us as we continue building our independent implementation
          of Java SE.
          (<i>2007-01-30</i>)
        </dd>        

        <dt>JDK Snapshot Available</dt>
        <dd>
          Apache Harmony now has a JDK snapshot available, that includes javac, keytool,
          and others. While not complete, it's our first step towards the standard
          JDK distribution format expected by developers. For more information, please
          see our <a href="download.cgi">downloads</a> page.
          (<i>2006-12-27</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Linux x86-64 (64-bit) Snapshots Available</dt>
        <dd>
          We now are including support for the x86-64 architecture under Linux.
          For more information, please
          see our <a href="download.cgi">downloads</a> page.
          (<i>2006-12-14</i>)
        </dd>

        <dt>Apache Harmony: Top-Level Project of the Apache Software Foundation</dt>
        <dd>
          Apache Harmony is now a top-level project of the Apache Software Foundation.
          On October 25th, the Board of Directors voted to make Apache Harmony a
          top-level project, and on October 29th the Apache Incubator PMC voted to
          graduate Harmony from the Apache Incubator, having satisfied the Incubator's
          requirements for community governance and IP oversight. We're in the process
          of transitioning our resources and infrastructure over, so please be patient
          while we do our move.
          (<i>2006-10-29</i>)
        </dd>

                <dt>New JRE and HDK Snapshots Posted</dt>
                <dd> Our <a href="download.cgi">latest snapshots</a> have
                        lots of new fixes and features. The VM has a new GC,
                        almost complete JVMTI, and now can co-exist with
                        <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/jdk/harmony">the IBM&#174; VME</a> in
                        the Harmony JRE structure. Our classlibrary continues to grow with new
                        classes, notably CORBA, thanks to <a href="http://incubator.apache.org/yoko">
                        Apache Yoko</a>.
                        Also, the classlibrary includes many new fixes and updates.
                        Choose the JRE to test your favorite applications, and
                        <a href="mailing.html">give us feedback</a> on how
                        we are doing, or use the HDK to enable faster development of the Harmony classlibrary.
                        (<i>2006-09-28</i>)
                 </dd>

                <dt>Can Apache Harmony Help Sun Open Java?</dt>
                <dd>We're happy to <a href="http://www.businessreviewonline.com/os/archives/2006/08/open_source_jav.html">help</a>
                        (<i>2006-08-16</i>)</dd>

                <dt>New Snapshot Posted</dt>
                <dd>Lots of fixes and additions in the latest snapshot. (<i>2006-08-16</i>)</dd>

                <dt>DRLVM Documentation Update</dt>
                <dd>Check our new documentation on <a href="subcomponents/drlvm/index.html">DRLVM</a>
                        including guides for building, using, debugging, GC architecture and execution manager
                        architecture. (<i>2006-08-05</i>)</dd>

                <dt>New HDK and JRE Snapshots Available</dt>
                <dd>New <a href="http://people.apache.org/builds/harmony/snapshots/">snapshots</a>
                        of the HDK and JRE are now available with lots of bugfixes. (<i>2006-08-04</i>)
                </dd>

                <dt>HDK and JRE Snapshots Available</dt>
                <dd>Harmony now <a href="http://people.apache.org/builds/harmony/snapshots/">offers a snapshot</a>
                        of it's JRE and HDK builds.
                        The JRE snapshot is our in-progress Java Runtime Environment,
                        including both the virtual machine and classlibrary. Note that
                        this isn't stable, complete or compatible software. However,
                        you can use this to run your favorite Java applications and
                        help the project find and fix bugs, and help direct our efforts
                        to complete the most popular parts of the classlibrary first. The HDK
                        snapshot is a developers build, complete with classlibrary jars and
                        native libraries, header files, and build scripts. (<i>2006-07-22</i>)
                    </dd>

                <dt>New class library snapshot build available</dt>
                <dd>A new stable snapshot of the class libraries code is available
                        for download from the <a href="download.cgi">Harmony downloads page</a>.
                        These are made available for people to evaluate and experiment
                        with the code. This snapshot contains the recently integrated
                        Swing, AWT, and Java2D code. As always, please report bugs
                        (and successes!) to the <a href="mailing.html">Harmony developers mailing list</a>.
                        (<i>2006-06-30</i>)
                  </dd>

                <dt>AWT, Java2D and Swing Code Contribution</dt>
                <dd>On May 30th, 2006 the Apache Harmony project received a
                        <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HARMONY-528">
                        substantial contribution</a> of class library code into the project.
                        The code for AWT, Java2D, and Swing implementation has been contributed by Alexey
                        Petrenko on behalf of Intel corp. The full announcement can be found
                        on the <a href="mailing.html">Harmony developers mailing list</a>. Thanks to
                        Alexey and his colleagues in the Intel Middleware Products Division!
                        (<i>2006-05-31</i>)
                </dd>

                <dt>New class library snapshot build available</dt>
                <dd> A new stable snapshot of the class libraries code is available
                        for download from the <a href="download.cgi">Harmony downloads page</a>.
                        There are source and binary downloads available for people to
                        evaluate and experiment with the code. As always, please report bugs
                        (and successes!) to the <a href="mailing.html">Harmony developers mailing list</a>.
                        (<i>2006-05-12</i>)
                   </dd>

                <dt>DRL Virtual Machine Contribution</dt>
                <dd>  On May 3rd, 2006 the Apache Harmony project received a
                        <a href="http://issues.apache.org/jira/browse/HARMONY-438">
                        substantial contribution </a> of virtual machine (VM) code into the project,
                        containing a JIT, core VM, GC, bytecode verifier, etc. This was contributed by
                        Andrey Chernyshev on behalf of Intel Corp. The full announcement can
                        be found on the <a href="mailing.html">Harmony developers mailing list</a>.
                        (<i>2006-05-03</i>)</dd>

                <dt>Java Security Code Contribution</dt>
                <dd>On December 30th, 2005 the Apache Harmony project accepted additional
                        class library code into the project. The code had been contributed by
                        Mikhail Loenko on behalf of Intel corp. The new class library code
                        includes security, cryptography, javax.net and unit tests. Thanks to
                        Mikhail and his colleagues in the Intel Managed Runtime Division!
                        (<i>2006-01-16</i>)
                </dd>

                <dt>VM Interface and Core Classes Contribution</dt>
                <dd>IBM has offered the Apache Harmony project a set of core
                        Java classes and an implementation of a VM/class library
                        interface. Tim Ellison wrote:<br />
                        <i>
                            "I'm delighted to be able to make a code contribution to the
                            Harmony project on behalf of IBM. The code comprises a concrete implementation
                            of the interface between virtual machine and class library that we have
                            been discussing recently, together with a set of core Java classes."
                        </i><br />
                        This contribution is sufficient to run Ant and the Eclipse Java
                        compiler, to provide a basic self-hosting environment. IBM also
                        made a version of their J9 VM
                        <a href="http://www.ibm.com/developerworks/java/jdk/harmony">
                        available </a> for use by the project in evaluating this contribution.
                        Thanks Tim and IBM :) (<i>2005-11-08</i>)
                </dd>

                <dt>"Bootstrap JVM" Contributed to Apache Harmony</dt>
                <dd> Daniel Lydick made a contribution to the Harmony project of a basic Java Virtual Machine entitled
                        the "Apache Harmony Bootstrap JVM." Dan offered the VM with the following goals in mind:
                        <ul>
                            <li>Basic platform for learning about VMs</li>
                            <li>Boostrap and runtime framework for our eventual 'production' VM</li>
                            <li>Help spur architectural discussion about core component designs</li>
                        </ul>
                        Thanks Dan! (<i>2005-09-30</i>)
                </dd>

                <dt>Source for JCVM Contributed to Apache Harmony</dt>
                <dd>Archie Cobbs has offered for contribution to the Apache Harmony project
                        a copy of the <a href="http://jcvm.sourceforge.net/">JCVM</a> codebase. Come and
                        help us build on this interesting VM. Thanks Archie! (<i>2005-09-25</i>)
                </dd>

                <dt>Project accepted by Apache Incubator</dt>
                <dd>The Apache Harmony project was accepted formally accepted for
                        incubation by the Apache Incubator PMC. (<i>2005-05-18</i>)
                </dd>
            </dl>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
