<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<!--

    Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
    contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
    this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
    The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
    (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
    the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

    Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
    distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
    WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
    See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
    limitations under the License.
-->

<document>

<properties>
	<title>Apache Harmony - Getting Started For Users</title>
	<author email="harmony-dev@incubator.apache.org">Harmony Documentation Team</author>
</properties>

<body>

	<section name="Getting Started For Users">

        <p>
            The following instructions are for users that wish to use Apache Harmony
            for running their Java programs.  These steps require no development
            tools or necessitate the compilation source code.
        </p>
        <p>
            Any required dependencies are listed below per platform.
        </p>

    <subsection name="Download the Apache Harmony Snapshot">

        <p>
            The first step is to download the binary distribution appropriate to
            your platform.  We currently distribute binaries for Linux and Microsoft
            Windows.  Please follow the instructions on the <a href="downloads.html">download page</a>
            to choose and download the software.
        </p>
        <p>
            Currently, the Apache Harmony project has no formal releases of its software.
            Instead, the project is offering pre-built snapshots that
            are expected to run well on the platforms offered.
        </p>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Unpack the binary distribution">

        <p>
            Once you have optained the appropriate binary distribution, you need to unpack
            it on your machine.  In all cases, the distribution will unpack inÄto a <code>jre</code>
            directory.  We shall refer to this directory as the 'root directory' of the
            distribution.
        </p>

        <strong>Linux Users</strong>

        <p>
            If you are running Linux, you will need to use the <code>tar</code> program as follows :
        </p>

        <source>
$ tar -tzf latest-harmony-jre-linux.tar.gz
        </source>

        <p>
            This will unpack the JRE directory tree into the current directory.
        </p>

        <strong>Windows Users</strong>

        <p>
            If you are running Windows, you will need to use one of the many
            zip utilities available for windows to unpack the distribution.  Here are
            three popular ones, but anything that can handle a zip file will work :
        </p>

        <ul>
            <li><a href="http://www.info-zip.org/">Info-ZIP</a> (open source software)</li>
            <li><a href="http://www.7-zip.org/">7-Zip</a> (free software)</li>
            <li><a href="http://www.winzip.com/">Winzip</a> (commercial)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>
            Using the
            utility, extract the distribution zip file.  this will create the
            JRE directory tree.
        </p>
    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Configuring Your Environment">
        <p>
            Apache Harmony doesn't need any further environmental setup, but sometimes other
            programs do.  Also, it's convenient to have the Apache Harmony executables on
            your path.
        </p>

        <p>
            Generally speaking, you'll want to set your JAVA_HOME and PATH  environment variables.
            Exactly how to do this depends on the operating system and/or shell you are using.
        </p>

        <strong>Linux Users</strong>

        <p>
            The following works for the Bash shell.
        </p>


        <source>
$ cd jre
$ export JAVA_HOME=`pwd`
$ cd bin
$ export PATH=`pwd`:$PATH
        </source>

        <p>
            Note that this assumed your current directory was the parent directory of the
            Harmony JRE.  Also, please note those are 'backtick' characters, not apostrophes.
        </p>

        <strong>Windows Users</strong>

        <p>
            The following example assumes you unpacked the zip file into the root directory "C:\".
            Please adjust as necessary.
        </p>

        <source>
C:> cd jre
C:\jre>set JAVA_HOME=C:\jre
C:\jre> cd bin
C:\jre\bin> set PATH=C:\jre\bin;%PATH%
        </source>

    </subsection>

    <subsection name="Using Apache Harmony">

        <p>
            Now you should be ready to use Apache Harmony.  Note that we don't yet include
            <code>javac</code>, so continue to use the compiler from some other JRE.  You
            should be able to run programs normally.
        </p>

        <source>
$ java Foo
$ java -jar myjar.jar
        </source>


    </subsection>
    </section>
</body>

</document>
